the rank of a matrix is the number of
linearly independent rows that it has or
equivalently the number of linearly
independent columns the rank of a matrix
is always positive except in the case of
the zero Matrix which has rank 0. let's
go through five examples of calculating
the rank of a matrix we'll do the first
four real quick and we'll be a bit more
thorough with the last one here's a
matrix a it's not the zero Matrix so its
rank is positive generally to find the
rank of a matrix we'll want to put it
into row Echelon form doing this to a
gives us this Matrix and this tells us
the number of linearly independent rows
that a has it's simply the number of
non-zero rows in the row Echelon form in
this case we see that's three so the
rank of a is equal to three similarly
for this Matrix B if we put it into row
Echelon form this is what we get the
number of linearly independent it rows
in B is the number of non-zero rows in
the row Echelon form in this case there
are two non-zero rows so the rank of B
is two some matrices are simple enough
that we don't need to put them in row
Echelon form this Matrix C is not the
zero Matrix so it does have a positive
rank but I notice the two rows are not
independent the second row is simply
equal to negative two times the first
row so C has only one independent row
and its rank which we could also denote
like this is equal to one this Matrix D
has fewer columns than it has rows so it
may be simpler to look at the columns we
notice the first two columns are
linearly independent there's no way to
multiply column one to get column two
however column three is a linear
combination of the first two columns in
fact if we just add column one in in
column 2 that gives us column three so
the Matrix D has only two linearly
independent columns and we would say
that the rank of D is equal to two if
all else fails we can always put the
Matrix into row Echelon form and count
the non-zero rows let's do one more
example of that with this Matrix e we
want to make the entries below each
leading entry equal to zero so below
this two we want only zeros to get that
we'll set row two equal to row two minus
row four so those ones will cancel out
to get rid of this one we will subtract
row two from row four to again cancel
out the ones that gets us here we have
zeros below the two like we want now we
want to get zeros below the next leading
entry of negative one to make this two
equal to zero We'll add two copies of
row two into this third row and that
gets us here now we also want to get rid
of this one that's below the leading
entry of negative one and in order to do
that we'll simply add Row 2 to Row 4
which will eliminate Row 4 completely so
Row 4 is all zeros and we can see we are
now in row Echelon form and there are
three non-zero rows thus the rank of E
equals three thanks for watching let me
know if you have any questions